<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A proclamation of the Lords Iustices for the apprehension of the chiefe rebels: and the revvard for taking any of them: with the true and last newes from Ireland, and in what state Dublin stands at this present; sent from an honourable, and one of the chiefest persons there, to a nephew of his in London.</title>
            <author>Ireland. Lords Justices and Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87324</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I626A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E134_26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15631</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859901</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859901</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112003</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87324)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112003)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 24:E134[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A proclamation of the Lords Iustices for the apprehension of the chiefe rebels: and the revvard for taking any of them: with the true and last newes from Ireland, and in what state Dublin stands at this present; sent from an honourable, and one of the chiefest persons there, to a nephew of his in London.</title>
                  <author>Ireland. Lords Justices and Council.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Shepheard, and are to be sold at the signe of the Bible in Chancery-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641 [i.e. 1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dated on p. 12: Given at His Majesties Castle of Dublin February 8. 1641 [i.e. 1642].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112003:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A PROCLAMATION OF THE LORDS IV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices for the apprehenſion of the chiefe Rebels: AND THE REVVARD FOR TAKING ANY OF THEM:</p>
            <p>WITH The true and laſt Newes from Ireland, and in what ſtate Dublin ſtands at this preſent; Sent from an Honourable, and one of the chiefeſt perſons there, to a Nephew of his in London.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Shepheard,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Signe of the Bible in Chancery-Lane. 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:112003:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:112003:2"/>
            <head>By the Lords Iuſtices and Councell.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>W. Parſons. Jo. Borlaſe.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is well knowne to all men, but more particularly to his Majeſties Subjects of this Kingdome, who have all gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed plentifull and comfortable fruits of his Majeſties bleſſed government, how abundantly carefull his Majeſty hath been in the whole courſe of his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, of the peace and ſafety of this his Kingdome, and how graciouſly he hath laboured to derive to all his Subjects therein, all thoſe benefits and comforts, which from a moſt gracious King, could be conferred on his Subjects, to make them a happy people, whereof he hath given many great teſtimonies. And as at all times he endeavoured to give them due contentment and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, ſo even then whileſt the Rebels now in Armes were conſpiring miſchiefe againſt Him, and his Crowne and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, he was then exerciſing Acts of Grace and Benignity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, granting to his Subjects here the fulneſſe of their own deſires in all things, ſo far as with Honour or Juſtice he poſſibly could, and particularly when the Committees of both Houſes of Parliament here this laſt Summer attended his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in England, at which time (amongſt many other things graciouſly aſſented to by Him) he was content even with appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent loſſe and diſadvantage to himſelfe to depart with ſundry his Rights of very great value, which lawfully and juſtly hee might have retained, And as his continued goodneſſe to this people, and his Princely care of their proſperity and preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall (to the unſpeakable joy and comfort of all his good Subjects) render him glorious to all Poſterity, ſo the wicked ingratitude and treacherous diſloyalty of thoſe Rebels ſhall render them for ever infamous to all ages, and utterly inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:112003:3"/>even in the judgement of thoſe, who for any reſpect either formerly wiſhed well to their perſons, or now pitty them in their tranſgreſſions. And although the ſaid perſons now in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion were in no degree provoked by any juſt cauſe of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like griefe received from his Majeſty, or his Miniſters, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake ſuch deſperate wickedneſſe, neither can juſtly aſſigne any ſeverity or rigour in the execution of thoſe Lawes which are in force in this Kingdome againſt Papiſts, nor indeed any cauſe at all, other then the unnaturall hatred, which thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in Rebellion do beare to the Brittiſh and Proteſtants, whom they deſire and publikely profeſſe to root out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, The more ſtrange in that very many of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are deſcended of Engliſh, whence is the originall and foundation of all their eſtates, and thoſe great benefits which they have hitherto enjoyed, and whence their Predeceſſors, and others then well affected in this Kingdome, have been at all times ſince the Conqueſt cherriſhed, relieved, countenanced, and ſupported, againſt the ancient enemies of the Kings people of England, many of the Iriſh alſo having received their eſtates and livelihood from the unexampled bounty and goodneſſe of the Kings of England. Yet ſuch is their inbred ingratitude and diſloyalty, as they conſpired to maſſacre Us the Lords Juſtices and Councell, and all the Brittiſh and Proteſtants univerſally throughout this Kingdome, and to ſeize into their hands, not only his Majeſties Caſtle of Dublin, the principall Fort in this Kingdome, but alſo all other the fortifications thereof, though (by the infinite goodneſſe and mercy of God) thoſe wicked and devilliſh Conſpiracies were brought to light, and ſome of the principall Conſpirators impriſoned in his Majeſties Caſtle of Dublin, by Us by his Majeſties authority, ſo as thoſe wicked and damnable plots are diſappointed in the chief parts thereof, his Majeſties ſaid Caſtle of Dublin, and City of Dublin being preſerved, and put into ſuch a condition of ſtrength, as if any of them, or their adherents ſhall preſume to make any attempt thereupon, they ſhall (God willing) receive that correction, ſhame, confuſion and deſtruction, which is due to their treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and deteſtable diſloyalty. And in purſuit of their bloody intentions, they aſſembled themſelves in Armes in hoſtile man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:112003:3"/>with banners diſplayed, ſurpriſed divers of his. Majeſties Forts and Garriſons, poſſeſſed themſelves thereof, robbed and ſpoiled many thouſands of his Majeſties good Subiects, Brittiſh and Proteſtants, of all their goods, diſpoſſeſſed them of their houſes and lands, murdered many of them upon the place, ſtripped naked many others of them, and ſo expoſed them to nakedneſſe, cold and famine, as they thereof dyed, impriſoned many others, ſome of them perſons of eminent quality, laid ſiege to divers of his Maieſties Forts and Towns yet in his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties hands, and committed many other barbarous cruelties and execrable inhumanities, upon the perſons and eſtates of the Brittiſh and Proteſtants, men, women, and children, in all parts of the Kingdome, without regard of quality, age, or ſex. And to cover their wickedneſſe in thoſe cruell Acts, ſo to deceive the world, and to make way (if they could) to the effecting of their miſchievous ends, they adde yet to their wickedneſſe a further degree of impiety, pretending outwardly, that what they doe, is for the maintenance and advancement of the Kings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, whereas it appeares manifeſtly, that their aimes and purpoſes inwardly are (if it were poſſible for them ſo to doe) to wreſt from him his Royall Crown and Scepter, and his iuſt So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty over this Kingdome and Nation, and to deprive him and his lawfull Miniſters of all authority and power here, &amp; to place it on ſuch perſons as they think fit, which can no wayſtand with his Maieſties iuſt Prerogative, nor can any equall minded man be ſeduced to beleeve that they can wiſh well to his Royall perſon, or any thing that is his, who in their actions have expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſuch unheard of hatred, malice, and ſcorn of the Brittiſh Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as they have done. And ſuch is their madneſſe as they conſider not, that his ſacred Maieſty diſdaines to have his name or power ſo boldly traduced by ſuch wicked malefactors, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells having never in any age beene eſteemed fit ſupporters of the Kings Prerogative, much leſſe theſe, who (under counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance thereof) labour to deface and ſhake off his Government, and extirp his moſt loyall and faithfull Subjects of his other Kingdomes and here, whoſe preſervation (above and earthly things) is, and alwayes hath beene his Majeſties principall ſtudy and endeavour, which even theſe Traytors themſelves
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112003:4"/>have abundantly found with comfort, if they could have beene ſenſible of it; And whereas divers Lords and Gentlemen of the Engliſh Pale preferred Petition unto Us, in the behalfe of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and the reſt of the Pale, and other the old Engliſh of this Kingdome, ſhewing that whereas a late Conſpiracie of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was diſcovered, of ill-affected perſons of the old Iriſh, and that thereupon Proclamation was publiſhed by Us, wherein (among other things) it was declared, that the ſaid Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie was perpetrated by Iriſh Papiſts, without diſtinction of any, and they doubting that by thoſe generall words of Iriſh Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, they might ſeeme to be involved, though they declared themſelves confident, that We did not intend to include them therein, in regard they alleadged they were none of the old Iriſh, nor of their Faction or Confederacie, but (as they then pretended) altogether averſe and oppoſite to all their deſignes, and all others of like condition, We therefore to give the full ſatisfaction (having indeede at that time great confidence in their loyalty) did by Proclamation dated the 29. of October 1641. declare and publiſh, that by the words Iriſh Papiſts, We intended only ſuch of the old meere Iriſh in the Province of Ulſter, as were then Actors in that Treaſon, and others, who adhered to them, and that We did not any way intend or meane thereby any of the old Engliſh of the Pale, nor of any other parts of this Kingdome, then eſteemed good Subjects, We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then (as We conceived) well aſſured of their fidelities to the Crowne, and having experience of the good affections and ſervices of their Anceſtors, in former times of danger and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion. And indeede ſo beleeving were VVe in their faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe &amp; loyalty to the Crown, as We then alſo repreſented it into England for their advantage, and thereupon in the Order of the Lords and Commons in the Parliament in England con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Ireland, his Majeſties loyall Subjects of Engliſh blood, though of the Romiſh Religion, being ancient Inhabitants with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſeverall Counties and parts of this Realme are mentioned, as thoſe who have alwayes in former rebellions given teſtimony of their fidelity to the Crowne of England. And in further te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of the good affiance VVee had in their loyaltie, VVee iſſued Armes to the ſeverall Counties of the Engliſh Pale, the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112003:4"/>better to enable them to diſcharge their duties, in defending thoſe parts, and his Majeſties good Subjects therein, againſt the Rebels, upon deepe profeſſions of loyaltie made by them, and their ſeeming deteſtation of the loathſomneſſe of the crimes, and bloody guilts of the Rebells, which they for their parts profeſſed (with many oathes and proteſtations) to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre, and promiſed to oppoſe and reſiſt them, with all their power. And wee iſſued Armes alſo to many Noblemen and Gentlemen of the Pale, and elſewhere, of the Romiſh Religion, for the defence of their houſes, againſt the Rebells. Yet much contrary to the expectation of all equall minded men, and in deceit of the truſt repoſed in them by this State, and directly contrary, as to their loyaltie and dutie to his Majeſtie, ſo to the great profeſſions which they had ſo lately before made at this Councell Board, many of thoſe as well whole Counties, as par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons entruſted with thoſe Armes, revolted to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, caryed his Majeſties Arms with them, and ſo the Arms which were truſted into their hands, for the protection of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties good Subjects, they converted to the annoyance and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction (as much as in them lay) of thoſe good Subjects they were truſted to protect, and of this State and Government, and have not onely not reſiſted the Rebells, but have alſo joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with them, and they and the Rebels aſſembled in Armes in hoſtile manner, with banners diſplayed, againſt his Majeſtie, in beſieging ſome of his Townes, taking into their poſſeſſion by force or fraud many of his Majeſties Burroughs, walled and unwalled, and in committing murders, ſpoyles, robberies, and many deteſtable cruelties on his Majeſties good Subjects. And although thoſe of the Pale, pretended that they were not able to aſſemble or arme any ſtrength againſt the Rebells, yet lately they found meanes to aſſemble, and arme great multitudes to aſſiſt the Rebells againſt his Majeſties forces, and againſt his Majeſties Government, and this State, And as well the perſons who were the firſt Actors in this Rebellion, as alſo many others in the Engliſh Pale, and ſeverall other parts of the Kingdome, forgetting thoſe duties which (by the Lawes of God and man) are due from them to his Sacred Majeſtie, are ſo ungratefull to his Majeſtie for the great and abundant benefits and favours
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112003:5"/>from Him, and his Royall Father, and Predeceſſors derived to them, ſo inſenſible of the happineſſe which they (with all others in this Kingdome) enjoyed by his bleſſed Government, and ſo improvident to themſelves and their poſteritie, as they have preſumed moſt unnaturally to conſpire, raiſe, and act thoſe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable Treaſons and Rebellion againſt his Majeſtie, as is herein formerly mentioned, And for as much as thoſe Rebells, and particularly Sir <hi>Con Magenis</hi> of Newcaſtle in the Countie of Downe Knight, <hi>Patrick mac Cartan</hi> of Loghnelan in the ſaid Countie, <hi>Art oge mac Glaſny Magenis</hi> of Ilanderry in the ſaid County, <hi>Ever mac Phelim Magenis</hi> of Caſtlewelan in the ſaid County, <hi>Rory mac Brian oge Magenis</hi> late of Edenteecullagh in the ſaid County, <hi>Phillip mac Hugh mac Shane O Rely</hi> of Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linecarrig in the Countie of Cavan, <hi>Phillip mac Mulmorry O Rely</hi> of Liſmore in the ſayd Countie, <hi>Mulmorry mac Edmond O Rely</hi> of Cavet in the ſaid Countie, <hi>Hugh Boy mac Shane O Rely</hi> of Kilmore in the ſaid Countie, <hi>Owen mac Shane mac Phil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip O Rely</hi> of the ſame, <hi>Rory Magwyre</hi> of Haſſets-towne in the County of Farmanagh, brother to the Lord <hi>Magwyre, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nogh bane Magwyre</hi> of Carrow in the ſaid Countie, Uncle to the ſaid Lord <hi>Magwyre, Brian mac Cowcannaght Magwyre,</hi> of Tempoe, in the ſaid County, Sir <hi>Phelim O Neale</hi> of Kinard in the County of Tyrone Knight, <hi>Tirlagh Roe O Neale,</hi> brother to the ſaid Sir <hi>Phelim, Tirlagh Groome O Quin</hi> of Donoghmore in the ſaid Countie, <hi>Cormock mac Owin oge O Hagan</hi> of Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linecor in the ſaid County, <hi>Patrick Modder O Donelly</hi> of Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kanena in the ſaid County, <hi>Art mac Tirlagh mac Henry O Neale</hi> of Devernagh in the County of Armagh, <hi>Tirlagh mac Henry mac Tirlagh O Neale</hi> of the Fues in the ſayd County, <hi>Hugh oge O Neale</hi> of Aghadamph in the ſaid County, <hi>Donogh oge O Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie</hi> of Caſhell in the ſaid County, <hi>Collo mac Brian mac Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>howne</hi> of Balloghie in the County of Monaghan, <hi>Neale mac Kena</hi> of the Trough in the ſaid County, <hi>Coolo mac Ever mac Mahowne</hi> of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> in the ſaid Countie, <hi>Art Roe mac Patrick mac Art Moyle mac Mahowne</hi> of Fanahah in the ſaid County, Captaine <hi>Hugh mac Phelim Birne</hi> late of Balline<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cor in the County of VVicklo, <hi>Shane mac Brien mac Phelim Birne</hi> late of Carrigocroe in the ſaid County, <hi>Luke alias
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:112003:5"/>Feagh O Toole</hi> of Caſtlekeven in the ſaid County, <hi>Luke alias Feagh mac Redmond Birne</hi> of Kilcloghram in the ſaid County, <hi>Redmond mac Feagh Birne</hi> late of Kilvane in the ſaid County, <hi>Phelim mac Redmond Birne</hi> late of the ſame in the ſaid County, <hi>Dermot mac Dowlin Cavenagh</hi> of Ballidony in the Countie of VVexford, <hi>Lewis alias Liſagh mac Owny Dempſie</hi> of Rahynne in the Kings Countie, <hi>Art O Molloy</hi> of Rathlyan in the ſaid County, <hi>Hubert Fox</hi> of Kilcourſie in the ſayd Countie, <hi>Owen O Molloy</hi> of Clonekeene in the ſaid Countie, <hi>Florence mac Shane Fitz-Patrick</hi> of Caſtle-towne in the Queenes Countie, <hi>Barnabie Dempſie</hi> of Knockardegur in the ſaid County, <hi>Daniel Doine</hi> of Tenehinche in the ſaid county, <hi>Barnabie Fitz-Patrick</hi> of Raghdowny in the ſaid County, <hi>Iames mac Fergus mac Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell</hi> of Taghnekillie in the ſaid county, <hi>Francis mac Faghny O Farrall</hi> of the Mote in the County of Longford, <hi>William Farrall</hi> of Ballintobber in the ſaid County, <hi>James mac Conell Farrall</hi> of Tenelecke in the ſayd County, <hi>Oliver Boy Fitz-Gerrald</hi> of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> in the ſaid County, <hi>Pierſe Fitz-Gerrald</hi> of Ballyſonan in the County of Kildare, <hi>Maurice Euſtace</hi> of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle-Martin in the ſaid County, <hi>Nicholas Sutton</hi> of Tipper in the ſaid Connty, <hi>Roger alias Rory O More</hi> of Ballynah in the ſaid County, <hi>William Fitz-Gerrald</hi> of Blackhall in the ſaid County, <hi>Robert Preſton,</hi> brother to the Lo. Viſcount Gorma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtown, <hi>James Fleming</hi> lace of Slane in the County of Meath, brother to the Lo. Baron of Slane, <hi>Patricke Cuſacke</hi> of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rards-towne in the ſaid County, <hi>Edward Betagh</hi> of Moynaltie in the ſayd County, <hi>Gerrald Leins</hi> of the Knock in the ſayd County, <hi>Luke Netervill</hi> of Carballies in the County of Dublin, ſonne to the Lo. Viſcount Netervill, <hi>George Kinge</hi> of Clontarfe in the ſaid County, <hi>Richard Barnewall</hi> of Leſpopell in the ſaid County, Colonell <hi>Richard Plunket</hi> late of Dunſoghly in the ſaid County, <hi>Matthew Talbot</hi> late of Kilgobban in the ſayd County, <hi>John Stanley</hi> of Mallettſ-towne <hi>alias</hi> Marlettſ-towne in the County of Lowth, <hi>John Bellew</hi> of VVilletſ-towne in the ſaid County, <hi>Chriſtopher Barnewall</hi> of Rathaskett <hi>alias</hi> Rathasker in the ſayd County, and <hi>Oliver Caſhell</hi> of Dundalke in the ſaid County: In ſtead of that dutie and loyaltie, which his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties good and gracious Government might juſtly have wrought
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112003:6"/>in them, have returned nothing but thoſe fruits of Treaſon and Rebellion, to the diſturbance of the publique Peace, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of this Kingdome, and to the deſtruction (as much as in them lay) of this State and Government, and of the perſons and eſtates of many thouſands of his Majeſties good and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Subjects therein, whereby they have ſhewed themſelves to be moſt ungratefull, deteſtable, vile and unnaturall Traytors and Rebells, VVe therefore according to the cuſtome of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell Board in caſes of this nature (though no former Rebellion can paralell this for acts of crueltie and horrid crimes) doe by this preſent Proclamation in his Majeſties name, and by his Majeſties Authorities, declare, publiſh and proclaime them, the ſaid Sir <hi>Con Magenis, Patrick mac Cartan, Art oge mac Glaſny Magenis, Ever mac Phelim Magenis, Rory mac Brien oge Mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, Phillip mac Hugh mac Shane O Rely, Phillip mac Mulmorry O Rely, Mulmorry mac Edmond O Rely, Hugh Boy mac Shane O Rely, Owen mac Shane mac Phillip O Rely, Rory Magwire, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nogh Bane Magwire, Brian mac Cowcannaght Magwire, Sir Phe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m O Neale Tirlagh Roe O Neale Tirlagh Groome O Quin, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mock mac Owin O Hagan, Patrick Modder O donnelly, Art mac Tirlagh mac Henry O Neale, Tirlagh mac Henry mac Tirlagh O Neale, Hugh oge O Neale, Donnogh oge O Murchie, Collo mac Brien mac Mahowne, Neale mac Kena, Coolo mac Ever mac Mahowne, Art Roe mac Patrick mac Art Moile mac Nahowne, Captaine Hugh mac Phelim Birne, Shane mac Brien mac Phelim Birne, Luke alias Feogh O Toole, Luke alias Feogh mac Redmond Birne, Redmond mac Feogh Birne, Phelim mac Redmond Birne, Dermott mac Dowlin Cavenagh, Lewis alias Liſagh mac Owny Dempſie, Art O Molloy, Hubert Fox, Owen O Molloy, Florence mac Shane Fitz-Patrick Barnabie Dempſie, Daniel Doine, Barnabie Fitz-Patrick, Iames mac Fergus mac Donell, Francis mac Faghny O Farrall; William Fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes mac Conell Farrall, Oliver Boy Fitz-Gerrald, Pierſe Fitz-Gerrald, Maurice Euſtace, Nicholas Sutton, Roger alias Rory O More, William Fitz-Gerrald, Robert Preſton, James Fleming Patrick Cuſacke, Edward Betagh, Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald Leins, Luke Netervill, George King, Richard Barnewall, Colonell Richard Plunket, Matthew Talbot, John Stanley, John Bellew, Chriſtopher Barnewall</hi> and <hi>Olive Caſhell,</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112003:6"/>every of them, and all their and every of their partakers, aiders, maintainers, comforters, confederates, complices and aſſociats, apparant notorious, ungratefull, wicked, vile and unnaturall Traytors and Rebells, againſt our moſt gracious Soveraigne Lord <hi>Charles</hi> by the Grace of God King of England, Scotland, France and Ireland defender of the Faith; &amp;c. his Royall Crowne and dignitie of this Realme, and malicious oppugners of his Majeſties Royall Soveraigntie, Preheminences and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, willing therefore, requiring, warranting and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing all his Majeſties good and loving Subjects, to purſue and plague with fire and ſword, apprehend, deſtroy and kill, by all the wayes and meanes they may, all the ſaid perſons, their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers, ayders maintainers, comforters, confederates, compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; aſſociats, as apparant notorious, ungratefull, wicked, vile, deteſtable and unnaturall Traytors and Rebells. And We doe hereby make knowne to all men, as well good Subiects as all others, that whatſoever he or they be that ſhall betwixt this and the five and twentieth day of March next, kill and bring, or cauſe to be killed and brought unto Us, the Lords Juſtices, or other chiefe Governour or Governors of all this Kingdome for the time being, the Head of the ſaid Sir <hi>Philem O Neale,</hi> or of the ſaid Sir <hi>Con Magenis,</hi> or of the ſaid <hi>Rory Magwire,</hi> or of the ſaid <hi>Phillip mac Hugh mac Shane O Rely,</hi> or of the ſayd <hi>Collo mac Brien mac Mahon,</hi> who were of the Principall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators, and have beene the firſt and principall Actors in this preſent Rebellion, he or they ſhall have by way of reward, for every of the ſaid laſt named perſons, ſo by him to be killed, and his or their head or heads brought to Us, the Lords Juſtices, or other chiefe Governour or Governours of this Kingdome, as aforeſaid, as followeth: <hi>viz.</hi> for the head of the ſayd Sir <hi>Philem O Neale,</hi> One thouſand pounds, for the head of the ſaid Sir <hi>Con Magenis</hi> ſix hundred pounds, for the head of the ſaid <hi>Rory Magwire,</hi> ſix hundred pounds, for the head of the ſaid <hi>Phillip mac Hugh mac Shane O Rely,</hi> ſix hundred pounds, for the head of the ſaid <hi>Collo mac Brien mac Mahon</hi> 6. hundred pounds, and Pardon for all his or their Offences, that ſhall kill, and ſo bring in, or cauſe to be killed, and ſo brought in, the ſaid head or heads. And whoſoever ſhall within the ſaid time, by any
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112003:7"/>meanes ſlay, or kill, as aforeſaid, the ſaid Sir <hi>Philem o Neale,</hi> Sir <hi>Con Magenis, Rory Magwire, Phillip mac Hugh mac Shane o Rely,</hi> and <hi>Collo mac Brian mac Mahowne,</hi> or any of them, though ſuch perſon or perſons, ſo ſlaying or killing the ſaid Traytors, or any of them, bring not, or cauſe not to be brought to Us, the Lords Juſtices, or other chiefe Governour or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of this Kingdome, the head or heads of the ſaid Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor or Traitors: Yet being juſtly proved, ſhall forthwith upon proofe ſo made, receive the reward, <hi>viz.</hi> for the ſaid Sir <hi>Philem o Neale</hi> eight hundred pounds, for the ſaid Sir <hi>Con Magenis</hi> foure hundred pounds, and for the ſaid <hi>Rory Magwire,</hi> foure hundred pounds, for the ſaid <hi>Phillip mac Hugh mac Shane o Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> foure hundred pounds, and for the ſaid <hi>Collo mac Brien mac Mahowne</hi> foure hundred pounds, and pardon for all his or their offences, that ſhall ſo kill the ſaid laſt mentioned perſons, or any of them. And for as much as the other Rebels above na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, have moſt traiterouſly combined in the wicked and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable Councels of the ſaid five other perſons laſt above na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and have been partakers with them in this their moſt bloody deſigne, for the extirpation of the Brittiſh and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, and depriving his Majeſty of the Soveraignty of this His Kingdome of Ireland, many of which Rebels ſtand indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of High Treaſon. We doe therefore make knowne and declare to all men, as well his Majeſties loving Subjects, as all others; That whoſoever under the degree of a Knight, other then the ſaid <hi>Phillip mac Hugh mac Shane o Rely,</hi> and <hi>Collo mac Brien mac Mahowne,</hi> and other then the ſaid <hi>Luke Toole,</hi> and other then the children and grandchildren of the late traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly deſcended Traytor, <hi>Feagh mac Hugh Birne,</hi> and other then the ſaid <hi>Rory alias Roger o More</hi> (We not holding it ſit that the moſt malignant Conſpirators ſhould obtain pardon for ſo high and hainous offences, and the cauſeleſſe deſtruction of ſo many thouſands of Innocents, upon the only ſervice of cutting off perſons of no greater conſideration) ſhall betwixt this and the five and twentyeth day of March next, kill and bring, or cauſe to be killed and brought in to Us, the Lords Juſtices, or other chiefe Governour or Governours of this Kingdome, as aforeſaid, the head or heads of the ſaid
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112003:7"/>
               <hi>Patrick mac Cartan, Art oge mac Glaſny Magenis, Ever mac Phelim Magenis, Rory mac Brian oge Magenis, Phillip mac Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morry o Rely, Mulmorry mac Edmond o Rely, Hugh Boy mac Shane o Rely, Owen mac Shane mac Phillip o Rely, Donogh Bane Magwire, Brian mac Cowcannaght Magwire, Tirlagh Roe o Neale, Tirlagh Groome o Quin, Cormac mac Owin oge o Hagan, Patrick Modder o Denelly, Art mac Tirlagh mac Henry o Neale. Tirlagh mac Henry Tirlagh o Neale, Hugh oge o Neale, Donogh oge o Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chie, Neale mac Kena, Coolo mac Ever mac Mahowne, Art Roe mac Patrick mac Art Moyle mac Mahowne, Captain Hugh mac Phelim Birne, Shane mac Brien mac Phelim Birne, Luke alias Feagh o Tool<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Luke alias Feagh mach Redmond Birne, Redmond mac Feagh Birne, Phelim mac Redmond Birne, Dermor mac Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin Cavenagh, Lewis alias Liſagh mac Owny Dempſie, Art o Mol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loy, Hubert Fox, Owen o Molloy, Florence mac Shane Fitz-Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trick, Barnabie Dempſie, Daniel Doine, Barnabie Fitz-Patrick, James mac Fergus mac Donell, Francis mac Faghny o Farrall, William Farrall, James mac Conell Farrall, Oliver Boy Fiz-Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald, Pierſe Fitz-Gerrald, Maurice Euſtace, Nicholas Sutton, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger alias Rory o More, William Fitz-Gerrald, Robert Preſton, James Fleming, Patrick Caſacke, Edward Betagh, Gerrald Leins Luke Netervill, George King, Richard Barnewall, Colonell Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Plunk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tt, Matthew Talbot. John Stanley; John Bellew, Chriſtopher Barnewall, and Oliver Caſhell,</hi> or any of them, hee ſhall have by way of reward for every of the ſayd laſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned perſons, ſo by him to be killed, and his or their head or heads brought to Us, the Lords, Juſtices, or other chiefe Governour or Governours of this Kingdome, as aforeſayd, foure hundred pounds, and pardon for all his or heir Offences, that ſhall bring in, or cauſe to be brought in, the ſaid head or heads, and whoſoever under the degree of a Knight, as aforeſaid, other then the ſaid <hi>Phillip mac Hugh mac Shane o Rely, Collo mac Brien mac Mahown, Luke Toole,</hi> &amp; the children &amp; grandchildren of <hi>Feagh mac Hugh</hi> aforeſaid, &amp; the ſaid <hi>Rory alias Roger o More,</hi> ſhall by any meanes, within the ſaid time, ſlay or kill the ſaid Traytors, <hi>viz. Patrick mac Cartan, Art oge mac Glaſny Magenis, Ever mac Phelim Magenis, Rory mac Brien oge Maginis, Phillip mac Mulmorry o Rely, Mulmorry mac Edmond, o Rely, Hugh
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112003:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Boy mac Shane O Rely, Owen mac Shane mac Phillip O Rely, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nogh Bane Magwire, Brian mach Cowconnaght Magwire Tirlagh Roe O Neale, Tirlagh Groome O Quin, Cormock mac owen oge O Hagan, Patrick Modder O Donnelly, Art mac Tirlagh mac Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry O Neale, Tirlagh mach Henry mac Tirlagh O Neale, Hugh oge O Neale, Donogh oge O Murchie, Neale mac Kena, Collo mac ever mac Mahowne, Art Roe mac Patrick mac Art Moyle mac Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>howne, Captain Hugh mac Phelim Birne, Shane mac Brien mac Phelim Birne, Luke alias Feagh O Toole, Luke alias Feagh mac Redmond Birne, Rodmond mac Feagh Birne, Phelim mac Redmond Birne Dermot mac Dowlin Cavenagh, Lewis alias Liſagh mac Owny Dempſie, Art O Molloy, Hubert Fox, Owen O Molloy, Florence mac Shane Fitz-Patrick, Barnaby Dempſie, Daniel Doine, Barnaby Fitz-Patrick, James mac Fergus mac Donell, Francis mac Faghny O Farrall, William Farrall, James mac Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell Farrall, Oliver Boy Fitz-Gerrald, Pierſe Fitz-Gerrald, Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice Euſtace, Nicholas Sutton, Roger alias Rory O More, William Fitz-Gerrald, Robert Preſton, James Fleming, Patrick Cuſacke, Edward Betagh, Gerrald Leins, Luke Netervill, George King, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Barnewall, Colonell Richard Plunket, Matthew Talbot, John Stanley, John Bellew, Chriſtopher Barnewall;</hi> and <hi>Oliver Caſhell,</hi> or any of them, though ſuch perſon or perſons, ſo ſlaying or killing the ſayd Traytors, or any of them, bring not, or cauſe not to be brought to Us, the Lords Juſtices, or other chiefe Governour or Governours of this Kingdome, as aforeſaid, the head or heads of the ſaid Traytor or Treators, yet being iuſtly proved, ſhall forthwith upon proofe ſo made, receive the reward of Thee hundred pounds, for every of the ſayd laſt named per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo killed and proved, and ſhall have Pardon for all his or their Offences, that ſhall ſo ſlay or kill the ſayd Traytors, or any of them.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Given at His Majeſties Caſtle of Dublin <date>February 8. 1641.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Ormond Oſſory. R. Dillin, Cha. Lambert. Ad. Loftus. I. Temple. Cha. Coote. Tho. Rotherham. Fra. Willoughby. Rob. Meredith.</signed>
            </closer>
            <closer>God ſave the King.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Imprinted at Dublin. 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:112003:8"/>
            <head>A true Copie of a Letter from Dublin.</head>
            <p>THe Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> Lievetenant Generall of the Army in Ireland, and Sir <hi>Charles Coote,</hi> and Sir <hi>Simon Harecourt</hi> went out of <hi>Dublin</hi> lately to meete the Rebells, hearing they had lodged themſelves at the <hi>Naas,</hi> 12. miles from <hi>Dublin,</hi> it is moſt true the Rebells were there entertained, but when they heard of our Engliſh Forces comming, though they were ten to one, yet they durſt not ſtand to it, but ranne away and left the towne to be pillaged by the Souldiers, they found ſuch boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty there, as the Souldiers came loaden home; a iuſt puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to thoſe that had pillaged the poore Engliſh that lived there when this rebellion broke forth; that towne is deſtroyed, and our Engliſh horſe went ſix miles further to a place called <hi>Killcullen-bridge,</hi> where the Rebells were too, but there they ſhewed likewiſe their heeles in running away; that place they burnt, and returned ſafe without loſſe of a man, the Engliſh Souldiers likewiſe in their returne to <hi>Dublin</hi> burnt <hi>Caſtlemartin</hi> and other ſmall villages thereabouts; and the Commanders hanged about foureſcore rogues they catch't, and but one of the Engliſh men hurt; After their returne to <hi>Dublin</hi> the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh againe iſſued our of <hi>Dublin</hi> ſouthward upon the Rebells of <hi>Wickloe</hi> and <hi>Wexford,</hi> about five miles from <hi>Dublin</hi> and there they ran away too, ſo that had they but at <hi>Dublin</hi> a conſiderable ſupply of men, money, and munition, by Gods aſſiſtance they ſoone would rout the Rebells thereabouts. Three of the Kings Pinnaces about three weekes ſince went to releeve <hi>Tredagh,</hi> but it pleaſed God by the violence of weather ſo to devide them, that one of them was ſhipwract upon the Coaſt of Wales, and the reliefe by the others prevented for that preſent, yet how ever ſuch was the care of the Lords, Juſtices and Counſell there, that on the 14. of <hi>February</hi> laſt, they ſent nine ſmall veſſels againe with victualls and munition, and 400. men, and by that meanes hath againe releeved <hi>Tredagh.</hi> And for full incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to thoſe well diſpoſed perſons that ſhall venture their monies for the reducing that kingdome to its former condition according to the late propoſitions made in Parliament; all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112003:9"/>or moſt of the Nobility and Gentry, by Juries of their owne Counties are convicted of high Treaſon at the Kings Bench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bar in Dublin, ſo that their eſtates are in a very faire way to be forfeited, for they are convicted upon Record already, and the perſons ſo convicted are owners of as fine Lands as any are in England, and quantity ſufficient to ſatisfie five hundred thouſand pounds, if it be laid out: Our deare and good bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in England I hope by long delay will not let us ſuffer, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Gentlemen of good repute are in the Country in their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall houſes, holding out ſtill, which by delay will be utterly loſt, which will be a great diſhonour to the Engliſh Nation, that in foure moneth ſhould ſend over but a handfull of men, they are full of charity, and I hope they will not let us ſuffer death, for no other can any Engliſh expect that hath oppoſed, and fall into their hands; money is much wanting in Dublin, in ſo much that ſome of our Engliſh die for want of clothing; In Dublin we have ſtill Vipers left, Alderman <hi>James,</hi> one of the Aldermen of Dublin is committed to the Caſtle of Dublin, for holding intelligence with the Rebels and it is thought he will be hanged, his juſt deſert: Sir <hi>Nicholas White</hi> is likewiſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Caſtle, as ſuſpected for a dangerous man, being a very great Papiſt, and his Sons being in Rebellion; Thus is the true ſtate of Ireland about Dublin at this time.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
